Finding Aid for Northern Michigan Environmental Action Council records, 1980-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Northern Michigan Environmental Action Council records
1980-2005
Northern Michigan Environmental Action Council.
06108 Bn 2
The Northern Michigan Environmental Action Council is a Traverse City-based environmental watchdog group. Members are primarily from a region comprised of five counties in Northwestern Michigan including Grand Traverse, Leelanau, Benzie, Kalkaska, and Antrim counties, although some members who feel a special affinity for the region are from downstate or out of state. The papers document the councilâ??s attention to local environmental concerns and their interactions with various government agencies, corporate entities, and individuals in the name of sound environmental stewardship.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the organization (donor no. 9740 ) in 2006-07.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Northern Michigan Environmental Action Council was founded in 1980 as a response to the Big Rock Nuclear Power Plant operating near Charlevoix Michigan. Since then, the council has devoted itself to transportation management, land use, contamination cleanup, and parkland protection. The council's mission statement, "preserving the natural environment through citizen action and education", provides the master plan for their advocacy activities.
The council makes a policy of partnering with other regional and nation advocacy organizations including The Coalition for Sensible Growth (of which it is a charter member), The Anglers of the Boardman, Trout Unlimited, The Friends of the Crystal River, and the Sierra Club. Their interests have brought them into conflict with development firms, local and state governments, and corporate polluters.
The council continues to be active and more records are expected to be forthcoming.
The records of the council are divided into four series, reflecting general areas of interest to the organization: Land Use, Toxic Cleanup Efforts, Transportation, and Board Minutes. In turn, the subseries within these series reflect advocacy efforts or controversies that fall under the general category.
Subjects:
Northern Michigan Environmental Action Council.; Cities and towns--Growth--Michigan--Grand Traverse Bay Region.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan--Grand Traverse Bay Region.; Traverse City (Mich.); Grand Traverse Bay Region (Mich.); Grand Traverse County (Mich.); City planning--Michigan--Grand Traverse Bay Region.; Hazardous waste sites--Michigan--Grand Traverse Bay Region.; Crystal River (Mich.)
- Land Use, 1980-2000
  The Land Use series includes materials documenting an effort to prevent residential development and the construction of a golf course on the Crystal River, as well as records documenting NMEAC's fight to preserve the Grand Traverse Commons (former site of the state psychiatric hospital and asylum) as public parkland. Other documents reveal the efforts to prevent the construction of Grand Traverse Mall and to prevent development of North Fox Island.
  - Crystal River, 1980-1989
    - Correspondence Between Robert Kuras and The Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, 1986; 1987 (Box 1)
    - Department of Natural Resources Definition of Wetlands, undated (Box 1)
    - Facts and Figures, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Friends of the Crystal River, 1986-1989; undated (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes and Water Planning Commission, Wetlands Management, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Homestead Workshops, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Kuras, Robert, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Maps (Box 1)
    - Michigan Land Use, Wetlands, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Fishing Guide, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1986 (Box 1)
    - NMEAC, 1987 (Box 1)
    - The Northwoods Call, 1986; 1987 (Box 1)
    - Opinion Letters, 1986; 1987 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, Excavations and Landslide,1986 (Box 1)
    - Zoning Ordinance Amendment, undated (Box 1)
  - Grand Traverse Commons, 1993-2000
    - Amendment to the Adaptive Reuse Feasibility Study, 1993; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Botanical Garden Society of Northwest Michigan, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Committee to Preserve Building 50, 1999; 2000 (Box 1)
    - Department of Environmental Quality, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Grand Traverse Audubon Club, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Grand Traverse Commons Redevelopment Corp., 1995-2000 (Box 1)
    - Gray, Judson, Ford and Seaman, Attorneys at Law, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Maps (Box 1)
    - Michigan Department of Management and Budget, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles, circa 2000; undated (Box 1)
    - NMEAC, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Planned Redevelopment Districts, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Smith, Bryan, undated (Box 1)
    - Wade-Trim, Inc., Munson Medical Center Access Study, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Grand Traverse Mall, 1991-1992
    - Negotiations and Settlement, 1991-1992; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Newspaper articles, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Notes, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - North Fox Is, 1990-1992
    - Correspondence, 1990-1992; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Dempsey Report, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Environmental Impact Statement, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Leelanau Township Meeting, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Notes and Minutes, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Position Statements and Drafts, 1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Press Releases, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
- Toxic Cleanup Efforts, 1985-2002
  The Toxic Cleanup Efforts series documents efforts to force corporate polluters, including Cone-Drive Textron and T.C. Light & Power, to fund cleanup efforts at sites that were contaminated as a direct result of their industrial activities.
  - Cone-Drive Textron, 1986-2002
    - Boardman Lake Timeline, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Brownfield Redevelopment, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Circuit Court Abeyance of Suit, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Cone-Drive Textron Meeting Minutes, 2000-2002 (Box 1)
    - Department of Environmental Quality, 1997-2002 (Box 1)
    - Department of Natural Resources, 1985-1995 (Box 1)
    - Dixon Environmental Consulting, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Email, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, 1986-1998 (Box 1)
    - Maps (Box 1)
    - Michigan Economic and Environmental Roundtable, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Land Use Institute, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1998-2000; undated (Box 1)
    - NMEAC, 1997-2002 (Box 1)
    - Olson, Noonan & Bzdok, Attorneys at Law, 2000-2002 (Box 1)
    - PIRGIM, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Public Employees for Environmental Responsibility, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Site Access Agreement, 2002 (Box 1)
    - The Traverse Group, 1997-2001 (Box 1)
    - Traverse City, 1997-2001 (Box 1)
    - Trout Unlimited, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1998-2000
    - Cleanup Meetings, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Community Decision Making in Contaminated Sediment Cleanups, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Email and Letters, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, Cleaning Up Contaminated Sediment, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Hull Park Pollution Assessment, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1999; undated (Box 1)
    - NMEAC, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Traverse City, 1997; 1999 (Box 1)
  - T.C. Light & Power, 1985-1987
    - Environmental Protection Agency, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985; 1987 (Box 1)
    - NMEAC, 1987 (Box 1)
    - State of Michigan, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Traverse City Grayiron, 1987 (Box 1)
- Transportation, 1994-2004
  The Transportation series documents NMEAC's resistance to the construction of a bridge over the Boardman River that would connect Hartman and Hammond roads. Construction of the bridge was perceived as a threat to the ecological health of the river. The motivation of the Grand Traverse Board of Road Commissioners was called into question, and a lawsuit was brought against them. The bridge also came to be understood as a stepping-stone on the path to a Traverse City bypass. In such light, many parties with differing perspectives and motivations became involved in the controversy. During this period, members of NMEAC, together with The Michigan Land Use Institute, formed The Coalition for Sensible Growth. NMEAC remains a charter member of The Coalition for Sensible Growth and the coalition's records are included in NMEAC's record group, especially within the Hartman-Hammond Bridge subseries. Recent additions to the Hartman-Hammond Bridge subseries include a large amount of public comments concerning the bridge, both pro and con. The series also includes some documents concerning the development of roundabouts in Traverse City and concern over the construction of the new BATA Transfer station.
  - BATA Transfer Station
    - Miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Hartman-Hammond Bridge, 1994-2004
    - Acme Township, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Anglers of the Boardman, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Boardman River Crossing Mobility Study, 1997-2000 (Box 2)
    - Coalition for Sensible Growth (Box 2)
    - Community Advisory Committee, 1995-2000 (Box 2)
    - Community Workshop, 1997 (Box 2)
    - De Leuw Cather & Company of Michigan, Consultants, 1995-1996; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Department of Environmental Quality, 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Department of Natural Resources, 1995-1998 (Box 2)
    - Department of Transportation, 1988-2000 (Box 2)
    - East Bay Township, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Garfield Township, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Grand Traverse County Administrative Offices, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Grand Traverse County Board of Commissioners, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Grand Traverse County Natural Education Reserve and Surroundings, 1995-2000 (Box 2)
    - Grand Traverse County Road Commission
      - Contracts, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence and Memos, 1994-2000; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Environmental Assessment, 1995; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Meeting Agendas, 1999-2004 (Box 2)
      - Newsletters, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - JJR, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Leadership Grand Traverse, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Maps, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Land Use Institute, 1996-2004 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990-2000; undated (Box 2)
    - Neighbors of Boardman River, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Articles, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - NMEAC, 1996-2004 (Box 2)
    - Northwest Michigan Council of Governments, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Northwest Michigan Resource Conservation and Development Council, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Olson, Noonan & Bzdok, Attorneys at Law, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Participation Guidance Document Among Plaintiffs in the Hartman-Hartman-Three Mile Lawsuit, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Public Hearings
      - Public Comments, 2001 (Box 3)
      - Comments prior to Public Hearing, 1999 (Box 3)
      - Sign In Sheets, 1999 (Box 3)
      - Public Comments, 1999 (Box 3)
      - Comments Received After Public Hearing, 1999; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Public Hearings, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Resolution for Michigan Transportation Economic Development Fund, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Sierra Club, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Smart Roads, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Steering Committee Meeting Minutes, 1998-2005 (Box 3)
    - Stupak, Bart, Congressman, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
    - T.C. Talus, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Taxpayers for Common Sense, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Traverse City People Movers, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Traverse City Public Schools, 1996-1998 (Box 3)
    - Traverse City, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Department of the Interior, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Roundabouts, 1999-2000
    - Designs, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper articles, 1999 (Box 3)
- Board Minutes, 1991; 1999-2001
  The Board Minutes series consists of minutes from the board meetings of NMEAC. These minutes discuss the projects undertaken by NMEAC as well as other environmental issues they discussed. The records include handwritten minutes, typed minutes, and agendas.
  - July 19, 1991 (Box 3)
  - January 1999-December 2001, 13 folders (Box 3)